Guide to the Hugo Oehler: Factional Documents and Spanish Civil War Reports, Correspondence and Ephemera TAM.066
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Hugo Oehler: Factional Documents and Spanish Civil War Reports, Correspondence and Ephemera
1932-1937
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Oehler, Hugo
TAM.066
0.75 Linear Feet (1 box)
The Revolutionary Workers League of the U.S. was a Trotskyist group organized in 1935 by the Left Wing Group of the Workers Party, who had been expelled from the Workers Party (U.S.). The records contain letters and reports (1936-1937) written from Paris and Barcelona by League members Hugo Oehler and R. Martin, largely relating to political developments in the Republic of Spain from a Trotskyist perspective. The collection also includes printed ephemera in Spanish distributed by Spanish Leftist groups. Also included are sixteen folders of material compiled for "special issues" of International News, an internal bulletin of the Workers Party (U.S.), Left Wing Group. The bulletins reproduce documents relating to predecessor organizations, including the Communist League of America, and discussions pertaining to the formation of the Fourth International; correspondence in these files includes two 1933 letters to Oehler from James P. Cannon on the letterhead of the Communist League of America.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Hugo Oehler, 1975. The accession number associated with this gift is 1975.001.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Revolutionary Workers League of the U.S. was a Trotskyist group organized in 1935 by the Left Wing Group of the Workers Party, who had been expelled from the Workers Party (U. S.). After several months of internal conflict, at the October Plenum of 1935, Workers Party leaders James P. Cannon and Max Shachtman were able to mobilize a majority to reject the demand of the left faction for an independent publication, and to warn them against violation of party discipline. Shortly afterwards, Hugo Oehler, Thomas Stamm and their followers were expelled and established the RWL, of which Oehler served as National Secretary. The Revolutionary Workers League was the largest group to emerge from the Communist League of America and the Workers Party (U.S.). Oehler and Stamm had opposed the "French turn" in America, that is, the decision to join the Socialist Party in anticipation of attracting left wing socialists to the Trotskyist movement.
Hugo Oehler traveled to Spain after the outbreak of the Spanish Civil War and made contact with a wide range of Trotskyist and other leftist groups and individuals. He was an eyewitness to the May 1937 insurrection in Barcelona, described in his published account, Barricades in Barcelona(NY: Demos Press, 1937).
Scope and Content Note
Series I: Spanish Civil War: Letters, Reports, and Printed Ephemera, 1936-1937 is made up of two parts. The first consists of reports made by Hugh Oehler and R. Martin to party offices in Chicago and New York. These letters narrate the political developments of the war in Spain in 1937, with particular focus on Catalunya, Valencia, and Aragon. Written from a Trotskyist perspective, they describe both specific events, such as the Insurrection of May 3-6, 1937 in Barcelona, and the more general and theoretical dynamics of the politics of the region. Oehler's reports are detailed first-hand accounts and reflect upon cultural, political, and socio-economic activities with the utmost descriptive specificity. Also of note are accounts of meetings of the "Friends of Durruti," and accounts of logistical problems that Oehler confronted during his visits to Spain and Paris. The second part of the series consists of propaganda distributed by a variety of left-wing groups from Eastern/South-Eastern Spain. Several groups of propaganda photographs, distributed by the "Comissariat de Propaganda de la Generalitat de Catalunya," depict the aftermath of fascist bombardments in Barcelona and children killed by fascist bombs (possibly from the air-raid at Lérida). Three folders of propaganda flyers represent the spectrum of leftist organizations vying for power in Barcelona; best represented is the Partido Obrero de Unificación Marxista(POUM), but also included are the Federación Anarquista Ibérica(FIA), the anarcho-syndicalist group Confederación Nacional del Trabajo(CNT), the Alianza Internacional de Trabajadore(AIT), the Sindicat de la Frusta and various radical youth groups, including the Juventudes Libertarias. Some of this material is harshly anti-Republican and nationalist/separatist in nature.
Series II: International News "Special Issues," 1932-1936, consists of compilations of material intended for internal distribution to members of the Workers Party (U.S.)'s Left Wing Group. Each issue consists of documents, such as position papers, correspondence, draft proposals and resolutions, minutes, etc., often on a single theme. Most of the documents are concerned with practical and theoretical developments in the Workers Party and in closely related left-wing groups active during the period. Most are written by members of the Left Wing Group, including Oehler, Tom Stamm, Louis Basky, and Arne Swabeck. Some of the material contained in the "Special Issues" was included in the version of International News produced for wider distribution by the Left Wing Group beginning in 1935. Note that the dates listed for folders in Series II reflect the dates of individual documents included, not the dates of distribution of the "Special Issues."
Arrangement
Series I is arranged alphabetically; series II is arranged by "Special Issue" number.
The files are grouped into two series:
Missing Title
I, Spanish Civil War: Letters, Reports and Printed Ephemera, 1936-1937
II, International News, "Special Issues," 1932-1936
Right and left (Political science); Trotskyism |z Spain.; Syndicalism |z Spain.; Socialism |z Spain.; Black-and-white photographs.; Minutes (administrative records); Correspondence.; Trotskyism |z United States.; Periodicals.; Socialism -- United States.; Anarchism |z Spain.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Workers Party (1940-1949); Revolutionary Workers League of the U.S.; Partido Obrero de Unificación Marxista; Swabeck, Arne.; Cannon, James P. (James Patrick), 1890-1974.; Sindicat de la Frusta; Workers Party (U.S.). Left Wing Group; International news.; F.A.I. (Organization: Spain); Confederación Nacional del Trabajo (Spain); Communist League of America (Opposition); Catalonia (Spain). Comissariat de Propaganda; Amigos de Durruti; Alianza Internacional de Trabajadores; Stamm, Thomas.; Oehler, Hugo
- Series I: Letters, Reports and Printed Ephemera, 1936-1937.
  - Oehler, Hugo/Martin, R.: Letters and Reports from Spain, Feb 1937-Mar 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Oehler, Hugo/Martin, R.: Letters and Reports from Spain, Apr 1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Oehler, Hugo/Martin, R.: Letters and Reports from Spain, May 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Oehler, Hugo/Martin, R.: Letters and Reports from Spain, Jun 1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Oehler, Hugo: Timeline of War Events in Barcelona from Proletariat Perspective, Fragments of Letters, [1937] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Partido Obrero de Unificación Marxista (POUM): Letter from RWL (in Spanish), Sep 26, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Printed Ephemera: Cards and Currency, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Printed Ephemera: Leftist Propaganda Photos, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Printed Ephemera: Propaganda Flyers of Spanish Leftist Groups, Undated, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Printed Ephemera: Propaganda Flyers of Spanish Leftist Groups, Undated, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Printed Ephemera: Propaganda Flyers of Spanish Leftist Groups, Undated, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series II: International News, "Special Issues," 1932-1936.
  - Special #2: Documents on the New Turn of the International Communist League (ICL): Correspondence with Crux ("Organization Name of Leon Trotsky"), 1935 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Special #3: Suppressed Articles (Communist Conference in Gillespie, IL/ Correspondence between Oehler and Cannon), 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Special #4: Suppressed Articles: European War Threat and the ICL (Reports by Oehler and L. Basky), Undated, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Special #5: Workers Party Caucus: Minutes, Correspondence, etc., Undated, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Special #17: Expulsion of Joseph Zack and Simon Williamson from the WPUS: Correspondence, Undated, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Special #18: New York Plenum of the Workers Party: Correspondence, Resolutions, etc., Undated, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Special #19: New York Plenum: Resolutions, Statements, Reports, Undated, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Special #20: Pittsburgh Plenum of the Workers Party: Correspondence, Statements, Undated, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Special #21: Pittsburgh Plenum: Correspondence, Resolutions, Undated, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Special #22: Pittsburgh Plenum: Program of Action, Undated, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Special #27: Trade Union Dispute with Joseph Zach: Resolutions, Leaflet, Undated, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Special #31a: CLA Convention: Latin America and the "Negro Question", Undated, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Special #34: Declaration of Principles, Undated, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Special #36: CLA: International Question: Statements and Resolutions, Undated, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Special #37: CLA: International Question: Statements and Resolutions, Undated, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Special #39: CLA: New Party Dispute: Correspondence, Draft Programs, Undated, 1933-1934 (Box 2, Folder 9)